<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The path-way to justification, plainly proving I. What it is to be justified. II. That justification is by the faith of Jesus, and not by the works of the law. III. They only are justified that believe in Christ. IV. What it is to believe into Jesus Christ. V. The difference between the law of faith and the law of works, also the difference between the work of faith, and the works of the law is plainly stated. VI. Many objections answered. Written by Thomas Killcop.</title>
            <author>Killcop, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1043_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207954</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866968</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87720)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 154:E1043[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The path-way to justification, plainly proving I. What it is to be justified. II. That justification is by the faith of Jesus, and not by the works of the law. III. They only are justified that believe in Christ. IV. What it is to believe into Jesus Christ. V. The difference between the law of faith and the law of works, also the difference between the work of faith, and the works of the law is plainly stated. VI. Many objections answered. Written by Thomas Killcop.</title>
                  <author>Killcop, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "September 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Justification --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168958:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PATH-WAY TO JUSTIFICATION, PLAINLY PROVING
<list>
                  <item>I. What it is to be juſtified.</item>
                  <item>II. That juſtification is by the faith of Jeſus, and not by the works of the Law.</item>
                  <item>III. They only are juſtified that believe in Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>IV. What it is to believe into Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>V. The difference between the Law of faith and the Law of works, alſo the difference between the work of faith, and the works of the Law is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtated.</item>
                  <item>VI. Many objections are anſwered.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Thomas Kilcopp.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM: 3.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The righteouſneſſe of God (without the Law) is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, being witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets, even that righteouſneſſe of God, which is by the faith of Chriſt unto all, and upon all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed in the Year,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:168958:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168958:2"/>
            <head>THE PATH-WAY TO JUSTIFICATION.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GAL. 2.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Even we have believed into Jeſus Christ, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Christ, and not by the works of the Law, for by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be justified.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>L</hi> wrote this Epiſtle purpoſely to withdraw the <hi>Galatians</hi> from the works of the Law. They which had by <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching received the truth, were now by falſe teachers drawne aſide to Jewiſh cuſtomes, as Circumciſion, the obſerving of dayes, times, months and years, for which <hi>Paul</hi> chides them, diſdainful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly terming ſuch cuſtomes another Goſpel, and weak and begger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elements, and oftentimes he terms them the works of the Law, this term is uſual. <hi>Paul</hi> hath in chiding of them 3 onſets, one ends with the 2. chap. another with the 4. and the laſt with the Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>In his firſt onſet is a reproof for turning to another Goſpel, meaning the Law and the works of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He exhorts them to let him be accurſed that preacheth otherwiſe then what he had taught them, ver: 6, 7, 8, 9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, So to do he brings two Motives: firſt, becauſe what he had taught them was not of man but of God, verſ. 10, 11. for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168958:3"/>they knew that he had been ſo zealous of the Jews Religion as to perſecute the Church and truth of Chriſt, till God by revelation made truth known to him, revealing Chriſt in him, and then with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt demur he preached the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Motive to conſtancie in the truth, is his own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for 17 years together, of which he brings two inſtances; firſt, his not ſuffering falſe brethren to circumciſe his companion <hi>Titus,</hi> chap. 2. to verſ. 7. ſecondly, in not ſuffering <hi>Peter</hi> one of the three chief Apoſtles to bauk with the truth, in ſhunning to eat with the Gentiles, to the end of the chap. in which inſtance note.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He did reprove <hi>Peter,</hi> and that to his face.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The cauſe why, for he was to be blamed, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Peters</hi> ſin, he for fear of the Jews did ſhun to eat with the Gentiles, ver. 12, 13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His words of reproof, and therein firſt, he reaſoneth the caſe with <hi>Peter,</hi> why he a Jew, who had already lived as the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhould hereby force the Gentiles to live as do the Jewes; ſecondly, affirmeth to <hi>Peter</hi> theſe words, <hi>We who are Jews by nature and not ſinners of the Gentiles, knowing a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Christ, even we have believed into Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law, for by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified,</hi> the laſt part of the ſaid affirmation, I ſpeak from, wherein ſee 1. an end to obtain, to wit, <hi>Juſtification;</hi> 2. the means to obtain it, to wit, <hi>Chriſts faith and our belief, without the works of the Law. We have believed into Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> this is the preparative means on our part, <hi>that we might be juſtified,</hi> this is the end to obtain, <hi>by the faith of Chriſt,</hi> this is the executative means on Chriſts part, <hi>and not by the works of the Law:</hi> Levitical ſhadows tend not to juſtification; See here, a diſtinction between belief and juſtifying faith; one is ours, the other Chriſts; the one a preparative, the other the executative means, our beliefe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes Chriſts faith to juſtification, but the works of the Law are wholly excluded, but the preparative means on our part is not a bare belief, but a belief into Chriſt, the word is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, not <hi>in,</hi> but <hi>into,</hi> as Schollars affirm. Doctrines are theſe,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That juſtification is the chief end to obtain here:</hi> This is the promiſe to <hi>Abraham,</hi> the price of our high calling, but to this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:168958:3"/>all do aſcent, but the truth here held forth, and which will be oppoſed is this; <q>That our believing into Chriſt is a mediate, and Chriſts faith the immediate means of our juſtification, without the works of the Law.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This I ſhall firſt prove, and then declare the marrow of it, to prove it I ſhall prove four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſts faith is a means of our juſtification.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That our belief into Chriſt is a means alſo.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Our belief is a mediate, and Chriſt faith is the immediate means.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And all this without the works of the Law.</p>
            <p>That juſtification is by the faith of Chriſt, and that it is not by the works of the Law, is the thing affirmed. That our belief is a means preparative, and Chriſts faith the alone means executa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, is here included, <hi>We have believed into Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt,</hi> mark it, they had already belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into Chriſt, and to this end, to be juſtified by Chriſts faith, but ſee it alſo by other Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That Chriſts faith is a means of juſtification, for God doth <hi>juſtifie the circumciſed by faith, and the uncircumciſed through faith;</hi> Rom. 3.30. by faith, to wit, the faith of Chriſt, for <hi>Paul</hi> after his converſion to Chriſt, deſired <hi>to be found in Chriſt,</hi> that is, ſaith he, <hi>not having my own righteouſneſs, but that which is by the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith,</hi> Phil: 3.8, 9. none are juſtified, but by the faith of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mans believing into Chriſt is alſo a means leading thereto, for Chriſt Jeſus is <hi>ſet forth to declare Gods righteouſneſſe, that he might be juſt, juſtifying him that believeth into Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 3.26. None are by Chriſts faith juſtified, that do not firſt believe into Chriſt, becauſe God is juſt in juſtifying.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſts faith is the alone immediate means, nothing comes between that and our juſtification, but mans belief is a means mediate, or at a diſtance, for Chriſts faith comes between mans belief and his juſtification, for <hi>Gods righteouſneſſe is witneſſed by the Law and Prophets, even that righteouſneſſe of God which is by the faith of Chriſt, unto all, and upon all that believe;</hi> Rom. 3.21, 22. <hi>The Scripture hath concluded all under ſin, that the promiſe by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168958:4"/>the faith of Jeſus might be given to them that believe,</hi> Gal. 3.22. here we ſee that the promiſe, even the righteouſneſſe of God, is by the faith of Jeſus, that is the immediate means, but thoſe that it cometh to and upon, thoſe to whom it is given, do firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this is a means too, but at a diſtance. God worketh all things after the counſell of his own will, that we might be to the praiſe of his glory, who firſt truſted in Chriſt, <hi>In whom ye truſted after ye heard the word of truth, in whom alſo after ye believed, ye were ſealed with the holy ſpirit of promiſe, the earneſt of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> Eph: 1.11, 12, 13. We ſee here how according to the counſel of Gods will, belief is after hearing, and being ſealed with the holy ſpirit is after believing, and our inheritance is after ſealing: for the ſeal is but the earneſt thereof; juſtification is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore glorification, belief before juſtification, and Gods word before our belief: Note further, that Chriſts coming and dying is that that procureth our light by his word, <hi>this ſlain Lamb hath prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to open the book</hi> (of Gods will) Rev. 5. And Chriſt came be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the father in love ſent him, <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his only begotten ſon, that whoſover believeth into him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life,</hi> John 3.16.</p>
            <p>The firſt and moſt remote cauſe of mans juſtification, is the Fathers love ſending his ſon: The next, not ſo remote as that, is the ſons coming and dying: The third, not ſo remote as either of them, is mans enjoying the effect of Chriſts death: to wit, light with life: The fourth cauſe, not ſo remote as the three former, is mans well uſing life and light: The fifth and laſt cauſe, a cauſe not remote, but immediate, is the faith of Chriſt: The three firſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are common to all mankind, God ſo loved the world, and (by his ſon) faſhioneth all their hearts alike, Pſal. 33.14, 15. <hi>Enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth every one coming into the world,</hi> John 1.9. but mans belief is the firſt, and the faith of Chriſt the laſt ſpecial cauſe, <hi>all men have not faith,</hi> but one is a mediate, the other an immediate cauſe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The works of the Law are no means at all, <hi>a man is juſtified by faith, without the deeds of the Law,</hi> Rom. 3.20.27, 28. and ſo much for proof: But to prove theſe things and yet to miſunderſtand all, is to no purpoſe; Therefore ſee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168958:4"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What it is to be juſtified.</item>
                  <item>2. What the faith of Chriſt is by which we are juſtified.</item>
                  <item>3. What it is to believe into Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>4. What is meant by the works of the Law.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To be juſtified is to be made juſt, juſtifie, is (in the plaineſt Engliſh) make juſt, as purifie is make pure, purification, is making pure, or as glorifie, is make glorious, glorification, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king glorious, ſo juſtifie, is make juſt, juſtification, is making juſt; to be juſtified is to be made juſt, or righteous, as by Scripture alſo may appear, <hi>For as by one offence, judgement came on all to condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo by one righteouſneſſe the gift is toward all, to the juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, for as by one offence many were made ſinners, ſo by one righteouſneſſe ſhall many be made righteous,</hi> Rom. 5.18, 19. It is not by the offence of one, but by one offence, that many are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as the Tranſlater confeſſeth in the Margin. We are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for <hi>Adams</hi> act, God is not ſo partial or unequal in his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with man, as to ſet the childs tooth on edge, for the fathers eating ſowr grapes, as <hi>Ezck:</hi> 18. but by one offence, that is, luſting to ſin as he did, <hi>death came on all, becauſe all have ſinned,</hi> verſ. 14. We need not the imputation of his ſin to condemn us, for we have all luſted to ſin as well as he, which firſt luſting of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man is the mother that conceives ſin in him, read <hi>James</hi> 1.13, 14, 15. ſee another proof, <hi>He that knew not ſin was made ſin,</hi> (a ſin offering, as Iſa. 53.) <hi>for us, that we might be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God in him.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.21. the juſtified are made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            <p>Obj: <hi>But declaring juſt, is figuratively termed juſtifying, ſome juſtifie the wicked for a reward, and God juſtifieth the ungodly,</hi> Rom. 4.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But they are wicked that do ſo juſtifie the wicked, and a juſt God cannot ſo do, though he be exceeding <hi>gracious and merciful, yet he cannot clear the guilty,</hi> Exod: 20.7. &amp; 34, 7. Numb: 14.18. God can juſtifie, that is, make juſt one that was ungodly, but cannot account him juſt till he be ſo; <hi>If I ſin ſaith Job</hi> (a believer) <hi>thou markeſt me, and thou wilt not acquit me,</hi> Job 10.14. But if the unjuſt become juſt, doing what is lawful and right, God will account and declare him juſt, and not impute for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins to him, in caſe he ſin no more; as in <hi>Ezck:</hi> 18, 7, 8, 9.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168958:5"/>and <hi>Ezck:</hi> 33.14, 15, 16. God cannot wickedly juſtifie, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the ungodly to be juſt, while he remains unjuſt, but when he is juſt, God can juſtly account and declare him juſt, though he hath been unjuſt, and ſo to be juſtified is to be made juſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, But ſee alſo what the faith of Chriſt is, by which we are made juſt, and herein.
<list>
                  <item>1. What Chriſts faith is.</item>
                  <item>2. How we are juſtified by it.</item>
                  <item>3. How we may know we are juſtified.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, What is Chriſts faith? 1. His word is ſo called, <hi>The faith which Paul once deſtroyed,</hi> Gal. 1.23. <hi>The faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> James 3.1. Revel: 2.13. &amp; 14.12.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſts Spirit is ſo called, as the comparing of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will evidence, as, <hi>We have acceſs to the father by one ſpirit, acceſſe with confidence by the faith of him, Eph.</hi> 2.18. &amp; 3.12. <hi>Being juſtified by faith we have peace with God, and acceſſe to this grace wherein we ſtand,</hi> Rom. 5.1, 2. Here we ſee, that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt is the faith of Chriſt whereby we are juſtified. Again, Chriſt is <hi>ſaid to dwell in our hearts by faith,</hi> Eph. 3.17. that is, by his Spirit, for he dwells in none otherwiſe, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9, 10, 11. <hi>Ye are not in the fleſh but in the ſpirit, if the Spirit of God dwel in you, but if any have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is not his, and if Chriſt be in you,</hi> &amp;c. We here ſee that if the Spirit of God or Chriſt dwel in us, then Chriſt is in us and we are his, but elſe not, ſo that Chriſt by his faith, that is, by his ſpirit dwelleth in the juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and the Spirit of Chriſt is called the faith of Chriſt, for it is indeed the ſpirit of faith, 2. Cor. 4.13. though the word of Chriſt is the faith of Chriſt in the fruit, the Spirit of Chriſt is the faith of Chriſt in the root, and that by which we are juſtified. It is not his word meant here, for that precedes believing, but Chriſts juſtifying faith, is after our believing; and ſo, no leſſe then the Spirit of Chriſt juſtifieth: <hi>But ye are waſhed, but ye are juſtified, in the name of Chriſt, and by the Spirit of our God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. <hi>He that is leaſt in Zion ſhall be called Holy; When, even when the Lord ſhall have waſht away the filth of the daughter of Zion, by the ſpirit of judgement, and by the ſpirit of burning:</hi> Iſa. 4.3, 4. ſo that Chriſts ſpirit only is his faith by which we are juſtified.</p>
            <p>Secondly, See how we are juſtified by the faith or Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168958:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the conveyance of it and not otherwiſe, not by a bare imputation, but by a gift. <hi>Having given us his holy ſpirit,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.8. <hi>He that keeps his commandements dwelleth in him, and he in him, hereby we know we dwell in him, and he in us, even by the ſpirit which he hath given us,</hi> 1 John 3.24. &amp; 4.13. <hi>They that receive abundance of grace &amp; of the gift of righteouſneſs, ſhall reign in life,</hi> &amp;c. Rom. 5.17. <hi>He ſhall receive a bleſſing from the Lord, even righteouſneſs from the God of his ſalvation;</hi> Pſal. 24.5. See how juſtification is the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> a gift of righteouſneſſe, given and received, and ſo the juſtified are <hi>partakers of the Divine nature,</hi> therefore <hi>Let the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens drop from above, let the skies pour down righteouſneſs, and bring ſalvation; alſo, let the earth open, that righteouſneſs may ſpring up,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 45.8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>How know we that we are juſtified by the faith, or ſpirit of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> They to whom Chriſts ſpirit is given, <hi>are joyned to the Lord and but one ſpirit</hi> 1 Cor. 6.17. <hi>He that is born of the ſpirit is ſpirit,</hi> John 3.6. they are as Chriſt is; Chriſt dwels in them, and they in him, yea Chriſt lives in them, and they live by his faith, <hi>and all old things are done away, and all things</hi> in them <hi>are become new,</hi> thoughts, words, deeds and nature are new, they being new creatures, <hi>are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from glory to glory, as by the ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.18. &amp; 5.17. their love being perfected they (thenceforth) <hi>cannot ſin, becauſe they are born of God. He keepeth himſelfe pure, and the wicked one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not touch him,</hi> 1 John 3.9. &amp; 4.17. &amp; 5.18. The old man is cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and body of ſin deſtroyed in them, and for this very purpoſe, <hi>That thenceforth they ſhould not ſerve ſin, being dead, and riſen with Christ, they are freed from ſin,</hi> Rom: 6.5, 6, 7. The very root of ſin is took away if once juſtified, and ſo much to the ſecond particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, See next what it is to believe into Chriſt, and ſo
<list>
                  <item>1. What to believe into Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>2. What of Chriſt we muſt believe into.</item>
                  <item>3. What belief, is a belief into Chriſt.</item>
                  <item>4. That belief into Chriſt is a means of juſtification.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, To believe into Chriſt is to come unto, or into him by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, ſuch as enter not into him by believing, do not believe into him; <hi>He that cometh to me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall never hunger, and he that believeth on</hi> (into) <hi>me ſhall never thirſt,</hi> John 6.35. <hi>He that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168958:6"/>cometh to God, muſt believe that God is,</hi> &amp;c. Heb. 11. none can come to him without believing, but many believe without coming, but they believe not into Chriſt, except they come to Chriſt by believing; and therefore Chriſt exhorts men thus, <hi>If any man thirst, let him come to me and drink,</hi> and then explaines it thus, <hi>he that believeth into me, as ſaith the Scripture, out of his belly ſhall flow, &amp;c.</hi> John 7.37, 38. ſo then, to believe into Chriſt, is to come by believing to him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, What of Chriſt muſt we believe into, or come into; 1. Not into his perſon, <hi>which is far above the higheſt heaven,</hi> Eph. 4.10. 2. Not into his Spirit, entrance into that, himſelfe giveth us, by his own faith, after we have believed into him; but</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In general to believe into Chriſt, is to believe into his word; John 8.30, 31. <hi>As he ſpake theſe words many believed on him, (into him) and to theſe,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>if ye continue in my word, ye are my Diſciples indeed.</hi> 1. He preacht to them; 2. They believed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; 3. Theſe he encourageth to continue in his word, ſo that, to believe and abide in his word, is to believe and abide in him. <hi>If that which ye heard from the beginning ſhall remain in you, ye ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the Son, and in the Father,</hi> 1 John 2.24. <hi>I am the true vine</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ye the branches, he that abides in me, and I in him ſhall be fruitful,</hi> and what is this abiding in him, he tells us, <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ye abide in me, and my word abide in you,</hi> &amp;c. John 15.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. therefore let us while we have the light believe into the light, that is, into the word; believe into that, and ye believe into Chriſt, thus in general.</p>
            <p>Particularly, To believe into Chriſt, that is, into his word, is to believe into his name, and into his converſation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Into his name, <hi>as many as received him, to them gave he power to become Gods children, even to them that believed into his name,</hi> John 1.12. and they are condemned for not believing into him, which believed not into his name. John 3.18. We muſt believe into the outſide or profeſſion of his name, by yeelding to the Ordinance of dipping. <hi>Go ye therefore and diſciplize all Nations, dipping them, into the name of the Father, Son, and holy Spirit,</hi> Mat. 28.19. and into the inſide of his name, which is holineſſe, by ceaſing to ſin; <hi>Holy and Reverend is his name,</hi> Pſal. 111.9. <hi>Let every one that nameth the Lord Jeſus depart from iniquity;</hi> 2 Tim.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Believe into his converſation, that is, ſo to believe, as to <hi>put off (as concerning the converſation) the old man which is corrupt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168958:6"/>and put on the new man, which is after God created in righteouſneſs and true holineſs,</hi> Eph. 4.22, 23, 24. <hi>Put yeon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and make no proviſion for the fleſh to fulfil the luſts of it,</hi> Rom. 13. We ſee here, that to put on a new converſation is to put on the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; alſo to put it on or to enter into it, we know to be one and the ſame thing. <hi>Holineſs,</hi> the inſide of his name, is but the outſide of his converſation, <hi>and perfect right eouſneſs,</hi> the inſide of his converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we believe into: <hi>When with the heart we believe unto righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and witneſs with the mouth unto ſalvation,</hi> Rom. 10.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj:</hi> Is not the uſe of ordinances coming to Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thereby we draw nigh with our bodies, but if our ſpirit be not alſo brought unto him by ſubmiſſion to his will, our bodily draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh, will be in vain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, See what belief is termed a believing into Chriſt, or unto Chriſt. It is only a practical belief, that brings us to Chriſt, to his converſation, for <hi>belief with works is dead,</hi> that moves not, but lively ſtones, by a lively belief, come to Chriſt the living ſtone, 1 Pet. 1.1. to the 7. ſinning is going from Chriſt, and obedience, is coming to him. <hi>Draw nigh to God and he will draw nigh to you,</hi> how ſo, he tells us, <hi>cleanſe your hands ye ſinners, and puriſie your hearts ye double minded</hi> Jam. 4.7, 8. <hi>Come unto me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>all ye that are weary and I will give you reſt,</hi> how muſt we come? he tells us, <hi>Take my yoke upon you and learn of me, and ye ſhall find reſt to your ſoules;</hi> Matth: 11.28, 29. <hi>He is the author of eternal ſalvation, to all that obey him. He ſaves to the utmoſt all that come to God by him;</hi> Heb. 5.9. with Heb. 7.25. nothing but obeying him, is coming to God by him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Believing into Chriſt, or, obedience to his commands; is a preparative to juſtification, none are juſtified, till they firſt keep Gods law, and all ſuch obtain it. <hi>It is not the hearers of the Law that are juſt before God, but the doers of the Law, ſhall be juſtified.</hi> Rom. 2.13. ſuch as firſt obey him, he ſaves with an eternal ſalvation. If juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, then ſaved from the power, or roote of fin, and ſo fin can bud no more in them, therefore cleanſe hand, tongue, and heart from ſin, and <hi>thou ſhalt receive the bleſſing from the Lord, even righteouſneſſe,</hi> (a righteous ſpirit) <hi>from the God of thy ſalvation,</hi> Pſal. 24.5. <hi>He that believeth into me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving water, and this ſpake he of the ſpirit, which they that believed on him ſhould receive,</hi> John 7.38.39. Chriſts juſtifying ſpirit is not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without obedience preceding; and if perfect obedience pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168958:7"/>juſtification will through grace ſucceed. <hi>He that hath my commandements and keepeth them</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>he it is that loveth me, and he that loveth me, ſhall be loved of my father, and I will love him and will manifeſt my ſelf to him.</hi> This admirable promiſe made a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple ask him, how it was, or <hi>why it was that he would manifeſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to them and not to the world,</hi> and Chriſt again gives him the cauſe, ſaying, <hi>if a man love me, he will keep my word, and my father will love him, and we will come and make our abode with him,</hi> John 14.21, 22, 23. If we keep in a way of ſin, Chriſt cannot come to us, to juſtifie us, but if we leave ſin and walk in the way of righteouſneſſe, he will come to us, for <hi>he meeteth ſuch as rejoyce in working righteouſneſſe, which remember him in his wayes,</hi> Iſa. 64.5. let the ſinner leave ſin, <hi>and walk in all the ſtatutes of life, without ſinning again, and he ſhall live;</hi> that is, ſhall be juſtified, Chriſt ſhall live in him, and his life thenceforth ſhall be by the faith of the Son of God, <hi>Ezek:</hi> 33.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>Application.</head>
               <p>Then ſeek juſtification by a Godly life, <hi>While ye have the light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve into the light, that ye may be the children of the light;</hi> John 12.36. Adde to belief vertue, giving all diligence that all vertue may abound in you; for, then ye will not be barren in knowledge, then ye will make your calling and election ſure, and then ye ſhall never fall, becauſe an entrance will be miniſtred unto you, into the everlaſting Kingdome of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 2 Pet. 1. Therefore <hi>ſow to your ſelves righteouſneſſe, reap mercy, plough up your follow ground, for 'tis time to ſeek the Lord, till he come and reign righteouſneſſe upon you;</hi> Hoſea 10.12. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, keep judgement, do juſtice for my ſalvation is neer to come, and my righteouſneſſe to be revealed;</hi> Iſa. 65.1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Let this doctrin be alwayes taught, <hi>That believers be careful to maintain good workes, being profitable to men, Godlineſs is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to all things, having the promiſe of the life that now is, and that that is to come;</hi> Tit: 3.8. 1 Tim: 4.8. of juſtification here, and glorification hereafter, but if they draw back, God will have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them: and ſo much to the third particular.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, See what the works of the Law are, without which juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication muſt be, and herein
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168958:7"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. What works are called the works of the Law.</item>
                     <item>2. Why juſtification cannot be by them.</item>
                     <item>3. Application.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, To know what the works of the Law are, we muſt know what Law is ſpoken of, for the doing what any Law requireth, is the work of that Law, as Exod: 18.20. Chriſt and the Jews did in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral by the Law, mean all the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as Matth. 7.12. John 1.47. in which Law, are <hi>weighty matters, as judgement, mercy and faith,</hi> and ſlighter matters concern the Levitical worſhip, as Tithes and the like, <hi>Matth:</hi> 23.23. and <hi>Paul,</hi> whoſe words we have in hand, calleth ſometimes the whole, and ſometime each part, the Law.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Sometime (though ſeldome) he calleth the weightier part, even the ten commandements the Law, as in theſe words, <hi>He that loveth fulfilleth the Law, for this, thou ſhalt not commit adultery, thou ſhalt not kill, thou ſhalt not bear falſe witneſs, thou ſhalt not covet, or any other command is comprehended in this ſaying, Thou ſhalt love thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as thy ſelf, love doth his neighbour no ill, therefore is love the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the Law;</hi> Rom: 13.8, 9, 10. By Law here is meant the ten commands, alſo the ſame in Gal: 5.14.</p>
               <p>Secondly, He moſt uſually calleth the ſhadows of the Levitical Prieſthood the Law, and ſo, <hi>if the Prieſt-hood be changed, there is of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law.</hi> Were Chriſt on earth, he could not be a Prieſt, for there are Prieſts which <hi>according to the Law offer gifts.</hi> Again, <hi>Sacrifice and offerings, and burnt offerings, and ſin offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings thou wouldſt not, nor hadſt pleaſure therein, which are offered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law;</hi> Heb: 7.12. &amp; 8.4. &amp; 10.8. In ſuch places ſpeaking contemptibly of the Law, he meaneth by the Law, only Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical ſhadows: but preſſing us to keep the Law, then by the Law he meaneth the ten commands. Alſo, when <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of both, and would diſtinguiſh between them, then the ſubſtance is called <hi>the law of faith,</hi> and ſhadows called <hi>the law of works,</hi> and this without varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and as ſhadows only, is called the Law of works, ſo only the obſervation of ſhadows, he calleth the works of the Law, as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Rom. 3.27, 28. ſith <hi>Juſtification is by faith, boaſting</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is excluded, but by what Law? by the Law of works, Nay, but by the Law of faith, therefore we conclude, a man is juſtified by faith, without the deeds of the Law.</hi> The Law of works, or works of the Law is put in oppoſition to faith, or the Law of faith. Weak and beggerly ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168958:8"/>only are the works of the Law, without which juſtification is, as may further appear.</p>
               <p>Firſt, From the ſcope of this place, theſe words being part of <hi>Pauls</hi> reproof to <hi>Peter; Peter</hi> a Jew, knowing the partition wall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken down, had eaten with Gentiles, and afterward through fear of ſome Jews which came from <hi>James</hi> he withdrew, for which <hi>Paul</hi> ſharply reproves him, in which reproof he firſt reaſons the caſe with <hi>Peter,</hi> Why he a Jew that had already lived as the Gentiles, ſhould now (in ſo doing) <hi>compel the Gentiles to live as do the Jews,</hi> and then affirmed to <hi>Peter</hi> theſe words, <hi>We who are Jews by nature, and not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Gentiles, knowing that a man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt, have believed into Jeſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, and not by the works of the Law,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that, what <hi>Paul</hi> before called, <hi>living as the Jews,</hi> he now calleth, <hi>the works of the Law,</hi> and looking yet backward, we find the ſame termed, <hi>the Jews Religion,</hi> which is here termed, <hi>living as do the Jews,</hi> or <hi>works of the Law,</hi> as ch: 1.13, 14. Alſo looking forward, we find the ſame termed, <hi>wordly, weak and beggerly ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which is here termed, <hi>living as the Jews, and the works of the Law,</hi> with the nomination of ſome particulars, as obſerving of <hi>days, times months and years;</hi> ch: 4.3.9, 10, 11. and ſo it is not good works, but beggerly rudiments, and they only are the works of the Law, by which no fleſh is juſtified.</p>
               <p>Secondly, This very term (<hi>the works of the Law</hi>) never was by <hi>Paul</hi> or any Apoſtle applyed to <hi>good works:</hi> as the rule of righteouſneſſe, or <hi>law of faith,</hi> was never termed, <hi>the law of works,</hi> ſo obedience thereto, or good works, was never termed, <hi>the works of the Law.</hi> Read and conſider, Rom: 3.27, 28. Rom. 9.30, 31, 32. Gal: 3.10. It is not ſubmiſſion to the Law of faith, but to that law which is not of faith, which are termed the <hi>works of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, The current of Scripture confirmeth this, for to ſay we are juſtified without good works preceding, is as contrary to truth, as darkneſs to light. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, We are ſaid to be <hi>Juſtified by faith, without the deeds of the Law,</hi> but not without firſt keeping the Royal Law, if that be not firſt exactly kept, we ſhall never be juſtified, <hi>for it is not the hearers, but only the doers of the Law, that ſhall be juſtified:</hi> Rom 2.13. <hi>yet without the works of the Law,</hi> that is, without ſin offerings, though according to the Law.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:168958:8"/>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>All that are of the works of the Law are under the curſe,</hi> Gal. 3.10. What is every one that keeps the Royal Law accurſed? or, doth every good work a man doth, curſe him? or doth perfect walking, make him perfectly curſed? Nay, but the contrary, onely breakers of the Law are curſed, and only keepers of the Law are bleſt. <hi>Thou haſt rebuked the proud, they are curſed which doe erre from thy commandements,</hi> but, <hi>Bleſſed are the undefiled in the way, walking in the Law of the Lord: Bleſſed are they that keep his teſtimonies, that ſeek him with their whole heart. They do no iniquity, they walk in his wayes,</hi> Pſal. 119.1. 2, 3.21. <hi>Who ſo looketh in the perfect. Law of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and continueth in it, being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work, this man is bleſſed in his deed,</hi> James 1.25. See here, how they only are bleſſed that keep the Law, that do no iniquity, and they only are curſed that break it. <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, which walk not after the fleſh, but after the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.1. Yet very true, That all are accurſed, that are of the works of the Law: All that bring ſin offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ings, according to the Law, for they are ſinners, elſe they needed no ſin offering, only beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly elements are the works of the Law, and all that obſerve them are accurſed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, See why we cannot be juſtified by the works of the Law.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe they are but meer ſhadows, and out-ſides, and reach not the heart at all; <hi>Whereby were offered gifts and ſacrifices, which could not make him that did the ſervice perfect, as pertaining to the conſcience, which ſtood only in meats and drinks, and divers waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and carnal rites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Law having a ſhadow of good things to come, and not the very ſubſtance, can never with thoſe ſacrifices offered year by year make the comers thereunto perfect.</hi> Heb. 9, 10. and 10.1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The works of the Law brings curſe and condemnation, no fleſh can be juſtified by it, <hi>for thereby is the acknowledgement of ſin,</hi> Rom. 3.20. Sin offerings were appointed, in caſe men ſinne, not elſe, and ſo the bringers of a ſin offering, did thereby acknowledge themſelves ſinners, and therefore curſed; therefore as the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is the Miniſtry of the Spirit, Life, Righteouſneſſe, ſo this Law of works is the Miniſtry of the Letter, Death and Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:168958:9"/>
               <p>Thirdly, We cannot be juſtified by the works of the Law, for they nullifie Chriſts Prieſthood, were he on earth he could not be a Prieſt, ſith there are Prieſts that offer according to the Law, Heb. 8.4. and therefore we cannot be juſtified by the Law; and theſe are the reaſons. Now for Application.</p>
               <p>Firſt, To inform us of the difference between Law and Law, works and works, ſhadows and ſubſtance, and firſt of each Law: 1. That was the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> this is the Law of Chriſt; <hi>John</hi> 7.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2. 2. That was the Law of works, this is the Law of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.27, 28. 3. That was the yoke of bondage, this is the perfect Law of liberty. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1. <hi>James</hi> 1.25. 4. That was a Law of commands, contained in ordinances, meer ſhadows and not ſubſtance, <hi>Eph:</hi> 1.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. but this is the Royal Law, <hi>James</hi> 2.8. 5. That was the old, this is the new Teſtament, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.19. &amp; 9.1. 6. That is termed the letter and the fleſh, but this is termed the Spirit; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.3. 7. That is termed <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that now is, and in bondage with her children; this is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above, who is free, and the mother of us all; <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.24, 25, 26. 8. That was a Miniſtry or conveyance of the letter of death and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, whoſe glory is done away; but this is the Miniſtry or convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſpirit of life and righteouſneſſe, exceeding that in glory, and ſtill remaining; 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. 9. That was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by man in many great ſtones, ſet in the ground and plaiſtred, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.1, 2, 3, 4. but this God wrote in two ſmall tables carried in <hi>Moſes</hi> hand; <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.1.4. 10. That Law made nothing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but this the bringing in of a better hope doth; <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.19. See now the different works of each; firſt, in general. 1. Thoſe were the works of the Law, theſe the work of faith and labour of love; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3. 2. Thoſe were worldly, weak and beggerly elements, theſe are good works, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3.9. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.8. particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they differ. 1. Intheir circumciſions, that was but the circumciſion of the fleſh of an out-ſide <hi>Jew,</hi> this is mens circumciſing their hearts from ſin, to be infide <hi>Jews,</hi> in the ſpirit, not in the letter, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.28, 29. with <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. 2. That fleſhly circumciſion gave admittance to their paſſover, and other fleſhly priviledges; <hi>Exod:</hi> 12.48. but heart circumcifion admits to all Goſpel priviledges; as prayer, <hi>Job</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. hearing, <hi>James</hi> 1.21. baptiſme, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8. breaking bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3. In freewill offerings, thoſe were of beaſts, and by ſuch ſacrifices they covenanted with God,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168958:9"/>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5. But theſe are our bodies, which we preſent as a living ſacrifice, holy and acceptable, being devoted to Gods will, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38. 4. Touching Gods houſe, that was built of ſtones, and ſtood at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and thither they brought their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, to be offered by that carnal Prieſthood, but of this Saints are ſtones, lively ſtones, built up a ſpiritual houſe, a holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpiritual ſacrifices, acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.5. Touching paſſovers, they did yeerly feed on a Lamb, ſpotles in body and limb, with the mouth of their bodies, with ſowr hearbs, and unleavened bread; and in this poſture, ſtanding with ſhooes on their feet, ſtaves in their hand, their bodily loins girt, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to march to their earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> Exod. 12. but we muſt hourly feed on Chriſt our paſſover, ſpiritually eating his fleſh, drinking his blood (to wit his converſation by imitation) with ſorrow for ſins paſt, and with the unleavened bread of ſincerity and truth, our feet ſhod with the Goſpels preparation, in our hand the ſword of the Spirit, girding up the loins of our minds, <hi>looking for, and haſtning to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord,</hi> and our heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> the new earth, <hi>John</hi> 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7, 8, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16, 17. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.12, 13.6. About ſin offerings, they had ſuch a beaſt as the Law required, with confeſſion of ſin, by laying their hand on the head of their offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, but Chriſt is an offering for ſin, even for all mankind; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. which procureth pardon or forbearance for all, that they confeſſing and forſaking ſin may be accepted and obtain juſtification through the blood of Chriſt. 7. Touching waſhings, their work or ſervice <hi>ſtood only in meats and drinks, and divers waſhings and carnall rites till the time of reformation;</hi> Heb. 9.9, 10. but Gods will in this is our ſanctification, that we waſh our robes (our converſations) and make them white in the blood of the Lamb; 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14. 8. For rejoycing God-ward; they rejoyced every New-Moon, with ſinging, trumpets ſounding, muſick playing, melodious to the ear of man; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.1, 2, 3. but we <hi>muſt rejoyce in the Lord always, and ſpeak to our ſelves in Pſalms, Hymns, and Spiritual-ſongs,</hi> (to wit meditation on Gods mercies) <hi>ſinging and making melody in our hearts to the Lord.</hi> Phil: 4.4. Eph. 5.19. 9. Touching Tithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paying, in that Prieſthood, <hi>men that dye received Tithes, but in this, he that liveth;</hi> Heb. 7.8. We muſt give to further his truth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his diſtreſſed brethten, and what is ſo given, will be found in his record, as given to him: 3 <hi>John</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.40.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168958:10"/>10. In many appurtenances thoſe works had a golden out-ſide, a table, and ſtaves to bear it, all guilded, diſhes, ſpoons, cups, candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, ſnuffers, tongs, all of pure gold, <hi>Exod:</hi> 25. a linning ephod and a girdle, all wrought with gold, breaſt-plate, chains, bells, all of gold, and on <hi>Aarons</hi> head a plate of the pureſt gold when he entred the holy place, and with this Motto, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> Exod: 28. a golden out-ſide holineſſe; But Gods commands, and mans practical belief, are better then the pureſt gold; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. our garments of fine clean and white linnen is the righteouſneſs of Saints; Righteouſneſſe is our breſt-plate; Truth is our girdle wherewith our minds are girt; Churches that hold forth truth by word and deed are our golden cand leſticks, Read and weigh <hi>Rev:</hi> 19.8. <hi>Ephe:</hi> 6.14. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.12, 13. 20. In a word, the Law or withered Teſtament, had divine Ceremonies and a worldly ſanctuary and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, out-ſide ſervices and promiſes till the time of reformation; but Chriſt is come and hath a more excellent Miniſtry, better promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, better ſervices, a Miniſter of the holy things and of the true Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle which the Lord pitched and not man; <hi>Heb:</hi> 7.8. &amp; 9. Chapters, for was the Miniſtration of condemnation <hi>glorious, much more doth the miniſtration of righteouſneſs exceed in glory, was that that is done away glorious? much more is that that remains glorious,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.9, 10, 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="application">
               <head>The ſecond Uſe.</head>
               <p>Expect not ever to be juſtified without preceding good works; it is, and muſt be without the works of the Law; It is not, nor can be without good works preceding, we muſt do the law before juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Rom: 2.13. <hi>Was not Abraham our father juſtified by works, when he offered his ſon Iſaac on the Altar, ſo that his belief wrought with works, and by works was his belief perfected, and Scripture fulfilled, which ſaith, Abraham believed God, and it was counted to him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, ſee then, how that by works a man is juſtified, and not by belief only;</hi> The works by which he was juſtified was obedience, making no demur at the moſt difficult command, as the offering of his only ſon, if God bid him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj:</hi> But <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith he was not juſtified by works, he only belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that was counted righteouſneſſe; <hi>Rom:</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p>Anſw: <hi>Paul</hi> doth not oppoſe <hi>James,</hi> for he was not juſtified with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preceding good works, or obedience, which <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of; yet without the works of the Law, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of; <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth here, only ſuch works which the Jews were under, and Gentiles not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168958:10"/>under, and by the ungodly he meaneth only the none worſhipper in the Jews way, as the ſcope of the place may evidence to any that wink not. <hi>Paul</hi> had declared, chap. 3. that God is juſt in juſtifying only ſuch as believed into Jeſus; and ſo boaſting is excluded, not by the law of works, but by the Law of faith: therefore concludeth that a man is juſtified by faith without the deeds of the Law, and ſo God is a God not to the <hi>Jews</hi> only, but to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo, juſtifying the circumciſion of faith, and uncircumciſion by faith; which he further proſecutes, chap. 4. proving by two inſtances, that ſith juſtification is through faith, and not through works, therefore it comes to <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as to <hi>Jews.</hi> His firſt inſtance is Gods dealing with <hi>Abram,</hi> he being circumciſed, and a ſacrificer, might alſo (<hi>Jew</hi> like) have boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted before men of his workes, but not with God; Sith, God did not reckon ſuch works for his righteouſneſſe, but his practical belief, and ſo with all, (ſaith he) <hi>their belief</hi> (to wit, belief perfected by works as <hi>Abrahams</hi> was) <hi>is counted to them for righteouſneſs.</hi> His other inſtance is <hi>Davids</hi> deſcribing a bleſſed man to be one to <hi>whom right teouſneſs is imputed without works;</hi> to wit, without circumciſion, and ſuch works as made the <hi>Jews</hi> a people diſtinct from all people elſe, and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth it; ſaying, <hi>Came this bleſſedneſs on the Jews only, nay, but on the Gentiles alſo, for faith was reckoned to Abrvham for righteouſneſs before he was circumciſed, who afterward received the ſign of circumciſion, a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of the faith which he had before circumciſion, and ſo became father to all that believe though uncircumciſed, that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe might be imputed to them alſo, and the father of circumciſion, even of ſuch as walk in the ſteps of that faith which Abraham had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; for the promiſe was not to Abraham, or his ſeed through the Law, but through the righteouſneſs of faith; for, if they that are of the Law,</hi> (under circumciſion) <hi>be heirs, faith is void and the promiſe effectleſſe, but it is of faith, and therefore of grace, and ſo ſure to all the ſeed,</hi> all which are of <hi>Abrahams</hi> belief, be they Jew or Gentile: So we ſee <hi>Pauls</hi> drift in both Chapters isto prove, that ſith juſtification is not by the law of works, but by faith, Gentiles may have right to it as well as Jews, and ſo the works without which we are juſtified, are the works of the Law, and the Law through which Son-ſhip is not, or through which the promiſe doth not paſs, is the law of works, as chap. 3. and ſo, theſe ungodly ones (as tranſlated) which God juſtifieth, are before and after called Gentiles and uncircumciſion, not meaning ſinners, while they continue in ſin, or before they do good works, but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168958:11"/>the contrary, ſuch ungodly ones as walk in the ſteps of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, obeying every command as <hi>Abraham</hi> did, and the bleſſed ones to whom (as <hi>David</hi> ſaith) God imputes not ſin, were ſo ſanctiſied that in their ſpirit was (left) no guile, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 32.2, 3. yet without works, without circumciſion, and ſuch works as diſtinguiſhed Jew from Gentile, but not without the works of obedience, as <hi>James</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="application">
               <head>The third <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</head>
               <p>See the errors abroad about juſtification, (laid down as Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) anſwered and confuted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj:</hi> The labouring for a perſonal righteouſneſſe, or to be accepted with God for wel-doing, are the works of the law, or to ſeek by our well-walking to pleaſe God, is our own righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>Be not deceived, for God is not mocked, whatſoever any one ſoweth, the ſame ſhall he reap, he that foweth to the fleſh ſhall reap: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> and none reap life everlaſting that do not firſt ſow to the Spirit; <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7. No perſonal glory hereafter, without perſonal righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe now, and therefore <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; others laboured to be accepted of God for well-doing, and perſwaded others to it alſo, becauſe that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one <hi>ſhall at the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, receive according to that be himſelf hath done in the fleſh, whether good or bad.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.9, 10. and ſaith he, Col 1.10. <hi>Walk worthy of the Lord unto all well pleaſing.</hi> How to? He tells us being fruitful in every good work, God who abominateth the works of the Law, is not pleaſed without good works, and <hi>Paul</hi> and others that accounted their own righteouſneſſe but droſſe and dung, did by good works ſeek to win Chriſt, and to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>The Law (meaning the righteous rule) commands more then any can do, but enableth not, and knoweth no ſurety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though the law of works is a yoak of bondage, the law of faith is not ſo; <hi>Chriſt yoak is eaſie, his burden light, his commands are not grievous,</hi> Matth. 11. 1 John 5.3. They may be eaſily kept, for all the ten Commandements in their ſeveral branches and appurtenances in their utmoſt extent, can but require the right ordering of thought, word and deed, and canſt thou not do this? ſpeak ſinner, canſt thou not chooſe but deviſe miſchief on thy bed? and if Satan dart in vain thoughts, canſt thou not chooſe but lodge them? art thou neceſſitated to harbour them? <hi>Jer</hi> 4.14. or, art thou not able day and night to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on Gods Law? as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. &amp; 119.97. Secondly, Canſt thou not leave off curſing, and ſwearing, and lying, and railing, and fooliſh
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168958:11"/>jeſting; <hi>Eph:</hi> 4.25. &amp; 5, 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.13. or, art not able to ſpeak of wiſdome, or confer of judgement; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 37.30. Thirdly, Art thou neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to oppreſſe, or defraud, to cheat or ſteale, or kill, or commit adultery, &amp;c. Or, is not a rich ſinner able to cloath the naked, feed the hungry, harbor the deſtitute, <hi>Job</hi> 31.32. or to further Gods worſhip? or is any not able to yeeld to baptiſme, to prize Church meetings, and breaking bread in remembrance of Chriſt, and to prize prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying? Is any neceſſited to oppoſe Gods truth or people, or to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute them? or to believe lyes, that ſo they might be damned: ſpeak ſinner &amp; thy conſcience ſhall tel thee, that God hath enabled thee to ſhun all he forbids, and to do all he bids thee: Work out with fear and trembling thy own ſalvation, <hi>for God hath enabled thee to will and to do,</hi> Phil. 2.13.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>The Law is a long way to Chriſt, we muſt go all along till we come to perfection, before we can be juſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> There is no other, therefore no nearer way: Its onely the doers of the Law hall be juſtified, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.13. your new and nigh way of imputation is the high-way to deſtruction, for if Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe be reckoned yours, while you are a ſinner, by the ſame rule his glory muſt be reckoned yours when you are in hell.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>No ſin in the world can debar people from Chriſt, ſinners as ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are the objects of juſtification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The leaſt ſin remaining debars from Chriſt, for we muſt ſeparate from ſinners, and ſin too, ſo as not touch the unclean thing before he will receive us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>There is a paſſive receiving of Chriſt without a hand, when God foreeth open mans ſpirit, and powreth in his Son in deſpite of the receiver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This contradicts Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Behold I ſtand at the door and knock, if any man will open to me, I will come into him and ſup with him, and he with me,</hi> Rev. 3.20.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>The new Covenant requireth no condition on our part, and if we look to get by our duties it will be but a knock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw:</hi> Yea but it doth, the condition required before the promiſe of juſtification is made over to us, is no leſſe then perfection; Gen. 17.1, 2. <hi>Walk before me and be thou perfect, and I will make my cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Incline your ears to me, ſaith God, hear, and your ſoul ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David;</hi> Iſa: 35.3, 4.</p>
               <p>Obj. <hi>A man is juſtified when his ſin is not, and Chriſts righteouſneſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168958:12"/>is imputed to him though he ſin, and God ſeeth it as fighting againſt his holy Spirit, but ſeeth it not ſo as to condemn him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It hath been ſhewn that to be juſtified is to be made righteous, and that by the gift of the Holy Spirit, and though declaring the wicked to be juſt, is termed juſtifying him, yet ſuch juſtifying is abominable to God, for his ways are judgement without iniquity, juſt and right is he; Deut. 32.4. He cannot do that abominable thing which his ſoul hates, he cannot ſee ſin in any, but ſo as to condemn them, if a believing <hi>Job</hi> ſin, God mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him, and will not acquit him from his iniquity; <hi>Job</hi> 10.14. We muſt ceaſe ſinning before God can ceaſe condemning; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>If a believer ſin, Chriſt is reckoned the finner, and not he, for Chriſt doth all for him, others muſt do all themſelves, and God cannot be offended at them, but at Chriſt, God is well pleaſed in Chriſt, not with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>It is a deſperate thing to ſerve a rit of condemnation on a believer, though he fal into as groſs a ſin as the reprobate doth, the reprobate is curſt but not he, he is no no more curſed then if he had not ſinned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> A righteous God which hateth ſin, hates alſo the ſinner, and loves the righteous walker, read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.5, 6, 7. They and only they that ſin againſt him will he race out of his book, <hi>Exod.</hi> the ſoul that finneth it ſhall dye, <hi>Eze:</hi> He that doth righteouſneſs is righteous as he is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.7. God cannot hate one for the ſin of another, and it is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked concluſion to ſay, God is offended and diſpleaſed with Chriſt, for he could not be well pleaſed in him, were he not well pleaſed with him; <hi>He loved truth and hated iniquity, and therefore God his God did anoint him before his fellows;</hi> Pſal. 45.7 <hi>He alwayes kept his fathers commands, and therefore did always abide in his fathers love:</hi> John 15.9, 10. &amp; ſo ſhall we, if we ſo do.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>Chriſt is by imputation the greateſt ſinner under the whole cope of Heaven;</hi> Pſal. 40.12. <hi>for were he not a ſinner he could not die for ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some words in that Pſalm are applyed to Chriſt, being as true in him as in <hi>David,</hi> but v. 12. is not true in Chriſt, though true in <hi>David,</hi> and ſo are not applied to Chriſt, and Chriſt dyed for ſin not as a ſinner, but as a moſt holy ſin-offering, had the Father reckoned him a ſinner in dying for ſin, then muſt he die; firſt, for his own ſin, and again for the peoples ſin: Nay, had Chriſt been imputed a ſinner in dying for ſin, then muſt we all have periſht, and he alſo, although he had ſo died ten thouſand times over, for a ſin offering is moſt holy, and ſo accounted, as <hi>Lev.</hi> 6.17. &amp; 7.6. &amp; ſo was Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>Some were elect from eternity, and for them only Chriſt dyed, and for them he ſatisfied iuſtice, purpoſed faith, repentance and ſalvation, his death is ſufficient for all, but intended to be efficacious only to ſome.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168958:12"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> O how partial would God be if this were true, but he is impartial, as Chriſt dyed for all alike, and maketh all hearts alike, all ſouls being his, <hi>Ez:</hi> 18. So is he a like ready to elect one as another in caſe the one be as fit for election as another, for he electeth or <hi>ſetteth apart for himſelf the man that is Godly: Pſ.</hi> 4. <hi>The Father himſelf</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>loveth you becauſe you have loved me, and believed that I came from God,</hi> John 16.27. <hi>We are bound to bleſſe God for you brethren</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to a zealous people) <hi>Beloved of the Lord, becauſe God hath choſen you from the beginning, through ſanctification of the Spirit and belief of the truth;</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.13. We ſee here that God electeth only his ſpecial beloved ones, which ſpecial love of the Father to the creature, is occaſioned by love, and belief Godward in the creature, and by obeying the truth, theſe believers do purifie their own ſouls, as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. and when their Spirits are ſanctified by believing and obeying the truth, then comes Gods election; I ſay he elects them <hi>through the ſanctification of their ſpirit, and belief of the truth;</hi> firſt, God preached truth, then they believed and obeyed it: 3. their ſpirits came hereby to be ſanctified: 4. then God elected them, and not before.</p>
               <p>Obj: <hi>But they were elected from the beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, but not from the worlds beginning as ſome dream, but when by believing they had purified their ſouls thence forward are they the elect of God. <hi>Elect according to the fore knowledge of God, through ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the ſpirit, unto the obedience and ſprinkling of the blood of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.2. As election is before juſtification, or blood ſprinkling, ſo ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the Spirit is before election. Obj: <hi>But one place expreſly ſaith, as he hath choſen us in him before the world began,</hi> Eph. 1.4. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Had not the tranſlator favoured this error, he had tranſlated it from the foundation of the world, and then it would not have contradicted truth, for we elected ones have been elected from, or ever ſince that time, <hi>even through the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the ſpirit and belief of the truth,</hi> and not otherwayes. <hi>Abel</hi> in the firſt age of the world was elected after he had purified his Spirit by belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and obeying truth; So was <hi>Enoch</hi> in another age, <hi>Abraham</hi> in another age, <hi>Paul</hi> in another, and I hope ſome in this age alſo, and ſo, though Gods elect be choſen in Chriſt ever ſince the firſt age of the world, yet not cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen till after they are Godly, or till by belief they have ſanctified or puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied their own ſouls. Again, what man or woman was there ever ſince the world began, but hath been deceived by ſin, (except the man Chriſt Jeſus only) but neither Satan, not falſ teachers can deceive the very elect, to make them ſin, it is I ſay impoſſible for any to deceive them, <hi>Math.</hi> 24. Though they before election have been deceived as well as other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Then ſinner be not diſheartned to preſs after Godlineſs, for fear
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168958:13"/>thou art not elected (as ſome have been) for if thou art not elected, 'tis thy fault, and if thou art not as yet elected, thou maiſt be, if thou wilt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly practice Godlineſſe, and purifie thy ſoule by obeying truth. God is as free 1. to elect, then to juſtifie thee as any; he is as free for one as for another, witneſs his freeneſs to wicked <hi>Cain; Abel by belief offered a better ſacrifice then he, and obtained witneſs that he was righteous;</hi> Heb. 11. <hi>And God reſpected Abel and his offering, but not Cain nor his offering, at which Cain was wroth, and his countenance fell, then God ſaith to him, why art thou wrath, and why is thy countenance fallen, if thou doſt wel, ſhalt thou not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted? or elſe ſin lyeth at the door,</hi> Gen. 4. Why wroth <hi>Cain,</hi> thy conſcience ſhall witneſs that I rejected thee not without a cauſe, &amp; why is thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance falne? Doſt thou think thou art reprobated and paſt hope, and that my hatred is to thee irrevocable; no <hi>Cain,</hi> no ſuch thing, I am as ready to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of thee as of <hi>Abel,</hi> if thou wilt live as <hi>Abel</hi> doth; and though hitherto thou haſt deſerved diſpleaſure, ſhalt thou not be accepted if henceforth thou amend? let thy own conſcience judge; God is thus equal handed and open hearted to all, if any ſinner hearken to God, and turn from his evil ways, God will <hi>repent of the evil he purpoſed to do to them, and will not do it,</hi> Jer. 26.3. &amp; 36.3. If a man will alter his actions, God will alter his purpoſe, to elect a few &amp; reprobate many, without cauſe in the creature, but becauſe he wil do it, is partiality, &amp; partiality is not grace but cruelty, but to ſeekall mens good: is graciouſneſs, &amp; thus God is, he ſent his ſon, and his ſon came into the world purpoſely to ſave all. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.17. &amp; 12.47. <hi>Exerciſeth patience on purpoſe thut none ſhould periſh, but that all might repent;</hi> 2 Pet. 3.9. &amp; if ſinners but ſpeak well, it cheereth God, &amp; he heartily wiſheth their hearts were ſo, for their own good. <hi>De.</hi> 5.28, 29. But though God be ſo equal han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; open hearted to all, yet Lord how few attain juſtification; when the old world was fild with people, only one even <hi>Noah</hi> was in the way to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, who in time <hi>became heir of that righteouſnes which is by faith,</hi> Gen. 7.1. Heb. 11.7. In <hi>Jobs</hi> time, how many went the way to attain it, none all the earth over was like him, <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. he in time attained it, <hi>Job</hi> 42.5, 6. How many in the <hi>Jews</hi> times (though a Church of God) who were for multitude like the ſand, yet but a remnant ſaved. Iſa. 10.22. even one of a City, or two of a Tribe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. And in <hi>Pauls</hi> time, but a remnant, yet that was harveſt time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.35, 36, 37. Lord how few then are there in our times, which are but gleaning times of the juſtified, for our merciful Lord is juſt alſo, and cannot wickedly juſtifie any, <hi>but will finiſh the account and cut it ſhort in righteouſneſſe, the Lord will make a ſhort account on the earth.</hi> Rom. 9.28.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Page 9. line 16, for <hi>with,</hi> read <hi>without.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
